<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>

	<info>
		<name>Talien Talents</name>
		<description>Custom talents for Talien.</description>
		<author>B B</author>
		<update version="1.0.1">
			<file name="talien-talents.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/esmer-1/Talents-and-stuff/refs/heads/main/talents/talien/talien-talents.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Tempered Flame Stance" type="Feat" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_TALIEN_FEAT_TEMPERED_FLAME_STANCE">
		<description>
			<p>You are trained in a swordfighting style known as The Tempered Flame.</p>
			<p>As a bonus action on your turn, you can enter Tempered Flame Stance, gaining the following benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You are considered proficient in Dexterity saving throws.</li>
				<li>You gain a +1 bonus on attack rolls with light weapons.</li>
				<li>You can move up to 10 feet on your turn without provoking opportunity attacks.</li>
				<li>When you add a superiority die to a damage roll, you can choose for the superiority die's damage to be fire damage.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>You can exit the stance whenever you wish (no action required).</p>
			<p>If you ever fall prone or are subject to a condition that prevents you from moving, you automatically exit the stance.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet action="Bonus Action">
			<description>You enter Tempered Flame Stance and gain the following benefits: &#13;
			• You are considered proficient in Dexterity saving throws. &#13;
			• You gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls with light weapons. &#13;
			• You can move up to 10 feet on your turn without provoking opportunity attacks. &#13;
			• When you add a superiority die to a damage roll, you can choose for the superiority die's damage to be fire damage. &#13;
			• You can end the stance at any time, no action required. &#13;
			• The stance ends automatically if you fall prone or become unable to move.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Tempered Flame Maneuvers" type="Feat" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_TALIEN_FEAT_TEMPERED_FLAME_MANEUVERS">
	<description>
		<p>You gain an additional superiority die and learn two additional maneuvers. Blistering Strike and Flame Wave are added to the list of maneuvers you can choose from.</p>
	</description>
	<sheet>
		<description>You gain an additional superiority die and learn two additional maneuvers. Blistering Strike and Flame Wave are available as maneuver choices.</description>
	</sheet>
	<rules>
		<stat name="superiority dice:amount" value="1" />
		<select type="Class Feature" name="Maneuver" supports="Maneuver" />
		<select type="Class Feature" name="Maneuver" supports="Maneuver" />
	</rules>
</element>

<element name="Blistering Strike" type="Class Feature" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_TALIEN_MANEUVER_BLISTERING_STRIKE">
	<supports>Maneuver</supports>
	<description>
		<p>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to create a burst of brilliant light. You add the superiority die to the attack's damage roll, and the target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, it is blinded until the end of your next turn.</p>
	</description>
	<sheet>
		<description>When you hit with a weapon attack, expend one superiority die. Add it to the attack's damage roll, and the target makes a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, it is blinded until the end of your next turn.</description>
	</sheet>
</element>

<element name="Flame Wave" type="Class Feature" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_TALIEN_MANEUVER_FLAME_WAVE">
	<supports>Maneuver</supports>
	<description>
		<p>In place of an attack, you can expend two superiority dice to create a wave of fire in a line 30 feet long. Roll both dice and add your Dexterity modifier. Each creature in that line must make a Dexterity saving throw, taking that much fire damage on a failed save, or half as much on a successful one.</p>
	</description>
	<sheet>
		<description>In place of an attack, expend two superiority dice to create a 30-foot line of fire. Roll both dice and add your Dexterity modifier. Creatures in the line make a Dexterity saving throw, taking that much fire damage on a failed save, or half on a success.</description>
	</sheet>
</element>

	<element name="Deflect Blades" type="Feat" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_TALIEN_FEAT_DEFLECT_BLADES">
		<description>
			<p>You've trained to be able to deflect enemy sword strikes, ensuring you never take the full force of such an attack.</p>
			<p>Whenever you take slashing damage, you can reduce the damage taken by an amount equal to your proficiency bonus.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Whenever you take slashing damage, reduce the damage taken by {{proficiency}}.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

</elements>
