<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>

  <info>
    <name>Laurence Stuff</name>
    <description>Custom spells and spell changes for Laurence's campaign.</description>
    <author>esmer-1</author>
    <update version="1.0.1">
      <file name="custom-spells-v2.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/esmer-1/Talents-and-stuff/refs/heads/main/stuff/custom-spells-v2.xml" />
    </update>
  </info>
	
	<element name="Friends (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_FRIENDS">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>For the duration, you have advantage on all Charisma checks directed at one creature of your choice that isn’t hostile toward you. When the spell ends, the creature realizes that you used magic to influence its mood. The creature is not forced to become hostile, but you cannot cast this spell on that creature again until at least 7 days have passed. A creature might react negatively or seek retribution at the DM’s discretion, depending on the nature of your interaction with it.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a small amount of makeup applied to the face as this spell is cast</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Light (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_LIGHT">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You touch one object that is no larger than 10 feet in any dimension. Until the spell ends, the object sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet. The light can be colored as you like. Completely covering the object with something opaque blocks the light. The spell ends if your concentration ends, if you cast this spell again, or if you dismiss it as an action.</p>
			<p class="indent">If you target an object held or worn by a hostile creature, that creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw to avoid the spell.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school">Evocation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a firefly or phosphorescent moss</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Find Familiar (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_FIND_FAMILIAR">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You gain the service of a familiar, a spirit that takes an animal form you choose: bat, cat, crab, frog (toad), hawk. lizard, octopus, owl, poisonous snake, fish (quipper), rat, raven, sea horse, spider, or weasel. Appearing in an unoccupied space within range, the familiar has the statistics of the chosen form, though it is a celestial, fey or fiend (your choice) instead of a beast.</p>
			<p class="indent">Your familiar acts independently of you, but it always obeys your commands. In combat, it rolls its own initiative and acts on its own turn. A familiar can’t attack, but it can take other actions as normal.</p>
			<p class="indent">When the familiar drops to 0 hit points, it disappears, leaving behind no physical form. It reappears after you cast this spell again. As an action, you can temporarily dismiss the familiar to a pocket dimension. Alternatively, you can dismiss it forever. As an action while it is temporarily dismissed, you can cause it to reappear in any unoccupied space within 30 feet of you. Whenever the familiar drops to 0 hit points or disappears into the pocket dimension, it leaves behind in its space anything it was wearing or carrying.</p>
			<p class="indent">While your familiar is within 100 feet of you, you can communicate with it telepathically. Additionally, as an action, you can see through your familiar’s eyes and hear what it hears until the start of your next turn, gaining the benefits of any special senses that the familiar has. During this time, you are deaf and blind with regard to your own senses.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can’t have more than one familiar at a time. If you cast this spell while you already have a familiar, you instead cause it to adopt a new form. Choose one of the forms from the above list. Your familiar transforms into the chosen creature.</p>
			<p class="indent">Finally, when you cast a spell with a range of touch, your familiar can deliver the spell as if it had cast the spell. Your familiar must be within 100 feet of you, and it must use its reaction to deliver the spell when you cast it. If the spell requires an attack roll, you use your attack modifier for the roll.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 hour</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">10 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">charcoal, incense, and herbs that must be consumed by fire in a brass brazier</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">true</set>
		</setters>
		
	</element>

	<element name="Darkvision (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_DARKVISION">
		<supports>Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You touch a willing creature to grant it the ability to see in the dark. For the duration, that creature has darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. This darkvision functions even in magically created darkness, such as darkness created by the Darkness spell.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">8 hours</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">either a pinch of dried carrot or an agate</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Lesser Restoration (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_LESSER_RESTORATION">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Ranger, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You touch a creature and can end either one disease or one condition afflicting it. The condition can be blinded, deafened, paralyzed, or poisoned.</p>
			<p class="indent">In addition, this spell can be used to treat any wound that does not have specific criteria for treatment. It also cures wounds that specify magical healing as a treatment criterion.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Counterspell (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_COUNTERSPELL">
		<supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You attempt to interrupt a creature in the process of casting a spell. To cast Counterspell, you must name a spell that you know or have prepared which could reasonably counter the targeted spell. Counterspell must be cast using a spell slot at least equal to the level of the named spell. For example, a caster might name Fire Shield to counter a Fireball spell, but would need to cast Counterspell using a 4th-level spell slot to do so.</p>
			<p class="indent">If the creature is casting a spell of 3rd level or lower, its spell fails and has no effect. If it is casting a spell of 4th level or higher, make a Spellpower check. The DC equals 10 + the spell's level. On a success, the creature's spell fails and has no effect.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the interrupted spell has no effect if its level is less than or equal to the level of the spell slot you used.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">3</set>
			<set name="school">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 reaction, which you take when you see a creature within 60 feet of you casting a spell</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">60 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Dispel Magic (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_DISPEL_MAGIC">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Choose any creature, object, or magical effect within range. Any spell of 3rd level or lower on the target ends. For each spell of 4th level or higher on the target, make a Spellpower check. The DC equals 10 + the spell’s level. On a successful check, the spell ends.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, you automatically end the effects of a spell on the target if the spell’s level is equal to or less than the level of the spell slot you used.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">3</set>
			<set name="school">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 minute</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">120 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Elemental Weapon (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_ELEMENTAL_WEAPON">
		<supports>Paladin, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>A nonmagical weapon you touch becomes a magic weapon. Choose one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder. For the duration, the weapon has a +1 bonus to attack rolls and deals an extra 1d4 damage of the chosen type when it hits.</p>
			<p class="indent">In addition to being magical, the weapon also counts as an Elemental weapon. Its Elemental type depends on the chosen damage type: Elemental Air (lightning or thunder), Elemental Earth (acid or thunder), Elemental Fire (fire or lightning), or Elemental Water (acid or cold).</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th or 6th level, the bonus to attack rolls increases to +2 and the extra damage increases to 2d4. When you use a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the bonus increases to +3 and the extra damage increases to 3d4.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">acid,cold,fire,lightning,thunder</set>
			<set name="level">3</set>
			<set name="school">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Greater Restoration (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_GREATER_RESTORATION">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You imbue a creature you touch with positive energy to undo a debilitating effect. You can reduce the target’s exhaustion level by one, or end one of the following effects on the target:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>One effect that charmed or petrified the target</li>
				<li>One curse, including the target’s attunement to a cursed magic item</li>
				<li>Any reduction to one of the target’s ability scores</li>
				<li>One effect reducing the target’s hit point maximum</li>
			</ul>
			<p class="indent">Greater Restoration can also perform any function of Lesser Restoration.</p>
			<p class="indent">In addition, this spell fully removes wounds, bypassing any requirement for a long rest. It can heal wounds with specific treatment criteria unless those criteria explicitly state that Greater Restoration cannot be used.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">diamond dust worth 100 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Teleportation Circle (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_TELEPORTATION_CIRCLE">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>As you cast the spell, you draw a 10-foot-diameter circle on the ground inscribed with sigils that link your location to a permanent teleportation circle of your choice whose sigil sequence you know and that is on the same plane of existence as you. A shimmering portal opens within the circle you drew and remains open until the end of your next turn. Any creature that enters the portal instantly appears within 5 feet of the destination circle or in the nearest unoccupied space if that space is occupied.</p>
			<p class="indent">Many major temples, guilds, and other important places have permanent teleportation circles inscribed somewhere within their confines. Each such circle includes a unique sigil sequence - a string of magical runes arranged in a particular pattern. When you first gain the ability to cast this spell, you learn the sigil sequences for two destinations on the Material Plane, determined by the DM. You can learn additional sigil sequences during your adventures. You can commit a new sigil sequence to memory after studying it for 1 minute.</p>
			<p class="indent">Permanent teleportation circles may be protected so that only creatures with permission can arrive through them. Such circles typically require a specific key, token, sigil, or other authorization determined when the circle is created.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can create a permanent teleportation circle by casting this spell in the same location every day for one year. You need not use the circle to teleport when you cast the spell in this way.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">teleport</set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 minute</set>
			<set name="duration">1 round</set>
			<set name="range">10 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">rare chalks and inks infused with precious gems with 50 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<element name="Simulacrum (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_SIMULACRUM">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You shape an illusory duplicate of one creature that is within range for the entire casting time of the spell. The duplicate is a creature, partially real and formed from ice or snow, and it can take actions and otherwise be affected as a normal creature. It appears to be the same as the original, but it has half the creature’s hit point maximum and is formed without any equipment. Otherwise, the illusion uses all the statistics of the creature it duplicates, except that it is a construct.</p>
			<p class="indent">The simulacrum is friendly to you and creatures you designate. It obeys your spoken commands, moving and acting in accordance with your wishes and acting on your turn in combat. The simulacrum lacks the ability to learn or become more powerful, so it never increases its level or other abilities, nor can it regain expended spell slots. In addition, a simulacrum cannot cast Simulacrum.</p>
			<p class="indent">If the simulacrum is damaged, you can repair it in an alchemical laboratory, using rare herbs and minerals worth 100 gp per hit point it regains. The simulacrum lasts until it drops to 0 hit points, at which point it reverts to snow and melts instantly.</p>
			<p class="indent">If you cast this spell again using a 7th-level spell slot, any currently active duplicates you created with this spell are instantly destroyed. When you cast this spell using an 8th-level spell slot, you may have up to two simulacra active at the same time. When you cast this spell using a 9th-level spell slot, you may have up to three simulacra active at the same time. If casting this spell would cause you to exceed your maximum number of active simulacra, choose which existing simulacra are destroyed until you are within that maximum.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using an 8th-level spell slot, you can maintain up to two simulacra created by this spell. When you cast this spell using a 9th-level spell slot, you can maintain up to three simulacra created by this spell.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">7</set>
			<set name="school">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">12 hours</set>
			<set name="duration">Until dispelled</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">snow or ice in quantities sufficient to made a life-size copy of the duplicated creature; some hair, fingernail clippings, or other piece of that creature's body placed inside the snow or ice; and powdered ruby worth 1,500 gp, sprinkled over the duplicate and consumed by the spell</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	
<element name="Teleport (Laurence)" type="Spell" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_LAURENCE_STUFF_SPELL_TELEPORT">
	<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
	<description>
		<p>This spell instantly transports you and up to eight willing creatures of your choice that you can see within range, or a single object that you can see within range, to a destination you select. If you target an object, it must be able to fit entirely inside a 10-foot cube, and it can’t be held or carried by an unwilling creature.</p>
		<p class="indent">The destination you choose must be known to you, and it must be on the same plane of existence as you. Your familiarity with the destination determines whether you arrive there successfully. The DM rolls d100 and consults the table.</p>
		<table>
			<thead>
				<tr><td class="left">Familiarity</td><td>Mishap</td><td>Similar Area</td><td>Off Target</td><td>On Target</td></tr>
			</thead>
			<tr><td class="left">Permanent Circle</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>01–100</td></tr>
			<tr><td class="left">Associated object</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>—</td><td>01–100</td></tr>
			<tr><td class="left">Very familiar</td><td>01–05</td><td>06–13</td><td>14–24</td><td>25–100</td></tr>
			<tr><td class="left">Seen casually</td><td>01–33</td><td>34–43</td><td>44–53</td><td>54–100</td></tr>
			<tr><td class="left">Viewed once</td><td>01–43</td><td>44–53</td><td>54–73</td><td>74–100</td></tr>
			<tr><td class="left">Description</td><td>01–43</td><td>44–53</td><td>54–73</td><td>74–100</td></tr>
			<tr><td class="left">False destination</td><td>01–50</td><td>51–100</td><td>—</td><td>—</td></tr>
		</table>
		<p class="indent"><strong><em>Familiarity.</em></strong> “Permanent circle” means a permanent teleportation circle whose sigil sequence you know. Some permanent teleportation circles can be configured so that only creatures with permission can teleport to them. Such circles usually require a specific key, token, sigil sequence, or other authorization determined when the circle is created.</p>
		<p class="indent">“Associated object” means that you possess an object taken from the desired destination within the last six months, such as a book from a wizard’s library, bed linen from a royal suite, or a chunk of marble from a lich’s secret tomb.</p>
		<p class="indent">“Very familiar” is a place you have been very often, a place you have carefully studied, or a place you can see when you cast the spell. “Seen casually” is someplace you have seen more than once but with which you aren’t very familiar. “Viewed once” is a place you have seen once, possibly using magic. “Description” is a place whose location and appearance you know through someone else’s description, perhaps from a map.</p>
		<p class="indent">“False destination” is a place that doesn’t exist. Perhaps you tried to scry an enemy’s sanctum but instead viewed an illusion, or you are attempting to teleport to a familiar location that no longer exists.</p>
		<p class="indent"><strong><em>On Target.</em></strong> You and your group (or the target object) appear where you want to.</p>
		<p class="indent"><strong><em>Off Target.</em></strong> You and your group (or the target object) appear a random distance away from the destination in a random direction. Distance off target is 1d10 × 1d10 percent of the distance that was to be traveled.</p>
		<p class="indent"><strong><em>Similar Area.</em></strong> You and your group (or the target object) wind up in a different area that’s visually or thematically similar to the target area.</p>
		<p class="indent"><strong><em>Mishap.</em></strong> The spell’s unpredictable magic results in a difficult journey. Each teleporting creature (or the target object) takes 3d10 force damage, and the DM rerolls on the table to see where you wind up.</p>
	</description>
	<setters>
		<set name="keywords">teleport,force</set>
		<set name="level">7</set>
		<set name="school">Conjuration</set>
		<set name="time">1 action</set>
		<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
		<set name="range">10 feet</set>
		<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
		<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
		<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
		<set name="materialComponent" />
		<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
		<set name="isRitual">false</set>
	</setters>
</element>
	
</elements>
