<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>

	<info>
		<name>Allynna Talents</name>
		<description>Custom talents for Allynna.</description>
		<author>B B</author>
		<update version="1.0.0">
			<file name="allynna-talents.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/esmer-1/Talents-and-stuff/refs/heads/main/talents/allynna/allynna-talents.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Wizardry Training" type="Feat" source="Laurence Stuff" id="ID_ALLYNNA_FEAT_WIZARDRY_TRAINING">
		<description>
			<p>Thanks to Nevod Dorsk, you have received some training in the ways of the wizard, granting you these benefits:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>You can cast ritual spells as rituals.</li>
				<li>You can understand wizard spells and cast them from spell scrolls.</li>
				<li>You can attempt to learn additional spells from the sorcerer or wizard spell list. To do so, you must first acquire the spell from a scroll or spellbook. You must then study the spell for 4 hours per level of the spell, and then make an Arcana check with DC 10 + the spell's level.</li>
				<li>On a success, you learn the spell. On a failure, you must study the spell for a further hour per level of the spell before repeating the check. The hours need not be consecutive.</li>
				<li>You can learn a number of spells in this manner equal to your Intelligence modifier + your proficiency bonus, multiplied by 2.</li>
				<li>These spells count as sorcerer spells for you.</li>
			</ul>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You gain the following benefits: &#13;
			• You can cast ritual spells as rituals. &#13;
			• You can understand wizard spells and cast them from spell scrolls. &#13;
			• You can learn up to {{wizardry training:spells known}} spells from the sorcerer or wizard spell list. This equals (Intelligence Modifier + Proficiency Bonus) x 2. &#13;
			• To learn a spell, acquire it from a scroll or spellbook, study it for 4 hours per spell level, then make an Arcana check with DC 10 + the spell's level. &#13;
			• On a failure, study for 1 additional hour per spell level before trying again. The hours need not be consecutive. &#13;
			• These spells count as sorcerer spells for you.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
	<stat name="wizardry training:base" value="intelligence:modifier" />
	<stat name="wizardry training:base" value="proficiency" />
	<stat name="wizardry training:spells known" value="wizardry training:base" />
	<stat name="wizardry training:spells known" value="wizardry training:base" />

	<select type="Spell" name="Spell (Wizardry Training)" supports="Sorcerer" number="12" />
</rules>
	</element>

</elements>
